Guide to the General Collection Manuscript Music Miscellany
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Massenet, Jules, 1842-1912
  - Correspondence
    - Unidentified, 1898 Jun 8; 1 item (8 p.); 18 cm. (Box Folder 138)
      ALS, Paris, to "Très cher Monsieur," about Cendrillon.
    - Unidentified, 1911 Mar 26; 1 item (2 p.); 19 cm. (Box Folder 139)
      ALS, Paris, to "Monsieur le Ministre," recommending "M. Girone" as chef de la musique de la Garde Républicaine.
    - Unidentified, 1887 Feb 22; 1 item (3 p.); 18 cm. (Box Folder 140)
      ALS, Paris, to "Chère Madame," discussing Massenet's departure for Rouen and his recipient's singing.
      Stamp: "Collection R. Barbeyron".
      Purchased from Piere Berès on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund.
    - Unidentified, 1894 Dec 21; 1 item (1 p.); 18 cm. (Box Folder 141)
      Brief ALS, Paris, to "Monsieur," arranging a meeting with his recipient and a publisher.
      Purchased from Bernard Quaritch, Ltd., on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund.
    - Unidentified, 1885, n.d.; 2 items. (Box Folder 142)
      Two ANS, on visiting cards, to "Chère Madame," 1885 Nov 23, referring to a performance of Manon; and to "cher ami Fernand," undated.
    - Unidentified, 1910 May 8; 1 item (1 p.); 18 cm. (Box Folder 143)
      Brief ALS, Brussels, thanking his recipient.
    - Unidentified, 1881, 1892; 2 items. (Box Folder 144)
      Two ALS, Paris, to "Cher Monsieur" and "Cher Monsieur et ami," a musician friend in Barcelona, about a visit by Massenet to Barcelona, and referring to Les Erinnyes, 1881 Jun 12, and Le poète et le fantôme, 1892 Mar 8.
      Purchased from Poulain le Fur on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund.
    - Unidentified, 1903 Mar 5; 1 item (3 p.); 18 cm. (Box Folder 145)
      ALS, Palais de Monaco, containing a quotation of music and referring to Emma Calvé. Accompanied by a photograph of Massenet, undated, reproduced by Documentation générale photographique Roger-Viollet.
    - Unidentified, 1893-1904, n.d.; 6 items. (Box Folder 146)
      ALS, Paris, to "bien cher ami," 1893 Jun 6, thanking his recipient; ALS, "en voyage," to "Cher grand ami," 1901 Feb 10, returning a manuscript; brief AN on a visiting card, 1904 Jun 29; ALS, Paris, to "Cher ami," undated, about performance of a choral music by Delibes; ALS, Paris, to "Cher ami, n.y. Jun 24, about a trip to Spain; and ANS, Paris, undated, requesting tickets for Giselidis. Accompanied by clippings with reproductions of covers of sheet music by Massenet a reproduction of a photograph of Lina Cavalieri, and L'echo de Paris, illustrated supplement, 1892, about Werther.
      Purchased from Demarest on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund.
    - Unidentified, 1898 Nov 1; 1 item (1 p.); 18 cm. (Box Folder 147)
      Brief ALS, Paris, to "Pauvre chère Madame," about his recipient's daughter.
    - Unidentified, 1889 Nov; 1 item (1 p.); 18 cm. (Box Folder 148)
      ALS, Paris, to "Monsieur," thanking his recipient.
    - Unidentified, n.y. Nov 13; 1 item (1 p.); 18 cm. (Box Folder 149)
      Brief ALS, Paris, to "Mon bon ami," referring to Christoph Willibald Gluck.
    - Unidentified, 1886 Dec 18; 1 item (3 p.); 18 cm. (Box Folder 150)
      ALS, Paris, to "Cher ami," about his incidential music for Le crocodile, by Victorien Sardou.
      Purchased from Autographs S. A. on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund.
    - Unidentified, 1898 Mar 10; 1 item (7 p.); 18 cm. (Box Folder 151)
      ALS to "Cher grand ami," about performances of Manon, Thaïs, and Sapho.
    - Unidentified, n.d.; 1 item (1 p.); 18 cm. (Box Folder 152)
      Brief ALS, Vichy, to "Cher ami," referring to his return to Paris.
    - Unidentified, 1905 Mar 27; 1 item (1 p.); 19 cm. (Box Folder 153)
      Brief ALS to "Bien cher ami," thanking his recipient.
    - Unidentified, 1897 Jul 18; 1 item (3 p.); 18 cm. (Box Folder 154)
      ALS, praising his recipient's daughter.
    - Unidentified, 1879-1908, n.d.; 3 items. (Box Folder 155)
      Brief ALS, Paris, to "Cher ami," 1897 Apr 17, referring to a meeting with "Vicomte Delaborde"; brief ALS, 1908 Nov 17, referring to the Ménestrel; and ALS from Louise Massenet to "Madame," undated, thanking her recipient.
    - Unidentified, n.d.; 1 item (1 p.); 19 cm. (Box Folder 156)
      ALS, Avignon, to "Mr. le Secrétaire," about financial matters, his stay in Avignon, and mentioning Frédéric Mistral.
      Purchased from Alexander Autographs on the Walter Jennings Memorial Fund.
    - Unidentified, n.y. May 14; 1 item (3 p.); 18 cm. (Box Folder 157)
      ALS to "Cher ami," thanking his recipient.
      Purchased from Charavay on the Philip and Margaret Neufeld Fund of the Yale Library Associates.
    - Unidentified, 1885-1900, n.d.; 11 items. (Box Folder 158)
      ALS, Paris, to "Cher ami," 1885 Nov 6, arranging a meeting; ALS, Etretat, to "Cher confrère," 1888 Sep 15, about Gerhard Rosenkrone Schjelderup; ALS, Paris, to "Cher maître et confrère," 1890 Jan 1, and ALS, Paris, 1891 Mar 20, thanking his recipients; ALS, Paris, to "mon vieil ami," 1892 Jan 1, about his health and referring Werther and Le carillon; ALS, Paris, to "Madame," 1893 Feb 26, about their collaboration; ALS, 1896 Jun 15, about his return to Paris; ALS, Bordeaux, to "Mademoiselle," 1896 Nov 18, about her poetry; ALS, Paris, to "Cher et fidèle ami," 1896 Dec 30, thanking his recipient; ALS, Paris, 1900 Apr 4, arranging a meeting; and ALS, Versailles, to "Cher bon ami," undated, arranging a meeting with "Vizentini" and referring to Sapho and Thaïs.
    - Unidentified, 1904, n.d.; 3 items. (Box Folder 159)
      Brief ALS, 1904 Dec 12, referring to Chérubin and Mlle. Kerlord; and two visiting cards, with AN, undated, about a collaborator and a piano competition.
    - Unidentified, 1897 Nov 17; 1 item (4 p.); 18 cm. (Box Folder 160)
      ALS, Paris, to "Madame," about addition of her name to a list for his publisher Heugel, and referring to Marie-Magdeleine.
    - Unidentified, 1881, 1893; 2 items. (Box Folder 161)
      ALS, Paris, to "Madame," 1891 May 26, about her singing, La vierge, music he intends to write for her, and mentioning Gabriel Fauré; and ALS, Paris, to "Monsieur le directeur & cher confrère," 1893 Jun 16, about arrangements for performance of his music in Nancy.
    - Unidentified, [1868?] Apr 16; 1 item (1 p.); 14 cm. (Box Folder 162)
      ALS, about a visit from his recipient.
    - Unidentified, 1884 Oct 9; 1 item (1 p.); 18 cm. (Box Folder 163)
      Brief ALS, Paris, to "Cher ami," offering his a score to his recipient.
    - Unidentified, 1892 Oct 30; 1 item (4 p.); 16 cm. (Box Folder 164)
      ALS, Paris, to "Cher ami," discussing the success of a "protegée".
    - Unidentified, 1885 Mar 31; 1 item (4 p.); 18 cm. (Box Folder 165)
      ALS, Paris, to "Cher ami," discussing his health, music he intends to write for his recipient's poetry, and completion of Le Cid.
      Purchased from Autographe S.A. on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund.
    - Unidentified, 1907 Jun 18; 1 item (postcard); 9 x 14 cm. (Box Folder 166)
      ANS, written on a postcard, referring to his solitude and work, with a brief musical quotation.
    - Unidentified, n.d.; 1 item (calling card); 6 x 10 cm. (Box Folder 167)
      ANS on a visiting card, about a meeting.
    - Unidentified, 1906 Jul 28; 1 item (3 p.); 19 cm. (Box Folder 168)
      ALS, Egreville, giving directions from Paris to Egreville.
    - Unidentified, 1898, 1903; 2 items. (Box Folder 169)
      ALS, Versailles, 1898 Sep 14, declining an invitation; and ALS, Paris, to "Cher Monsieur," 1903 Nov 13, expressing thanks and referring to his recipient's return to Weimar.
    - Unidentified, 1894 Oct 15; 1 item (3 p.); 18 cm. (Box Folder 170)
      ALS, Paris, to "Chère Madame," referring to La Navarraise.
      Purchased from Richard M. Ford, Ltd., on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund.
    - Unidentified, 1902 Oct 24; 1 item (4 p.); 18 cm. (Box Folder 171)
      ALS, "de passage à Paris," to "Chère Mademoiselle et collaborateur," about Maria Morin.
      Purchased from Heritage Book Shop, Inc., on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund.
    - Unidentified, 1889 Jul 3; 1 item (4 p.); 17 cm. (Box Folder 172)
      ALS, Paris, to "Madame," regarding a recommendation for a position in a New York conservatory.
    - Unidentified, 1886 Aug 23; 1 item (3 p.); 18 cm. (Box Folder 173)
      ALS, Munich, to "Chère Madame," discussing his travels and referring to Richard Wagner.
      Purchased from Musikantiquariat Dr. Michael Raab on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund.
    - Unidentified, n.d.; 1 item (1 p.); 21 cm. (Box Folder 174)
      ALS, referring to a proof.
      Purchased R. M. Smythe & Co., Inc., on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund.
    - Unidentified, 1880 Jun 9; 1 item (2 p.); 16 cm. (Box Folder 175)
      ALS to "Cher Monsieur et ami," thanking his recipient for his response to La vierge.
    - Unidentified, n.d.; 1 item (1 p.); 19 cm. (Box Folder 176)
      ALS to "Cher ami," about performance of Le roi de Lahore in Angers.
    - Unidentified, 1879 May 13; 1 item (2 p.); 16 cm., bound in volume, 31 cm. (Box FOLDER 199)
      ALS, about music titled Marche heroïque.
      Bound with: Two engraved portraits; quotation from Werther; and Salutaris.
    - Unidentified, n.d.; 1 item (visiting card); 6 x 9 cm., bound in volume, 32 cm. (Box FOLDER 200)
      Printed visiting card with AN, offering good wishes.
      Bound with: Two photographs of Massenet; ALS to George Durrieu, 1909 Jul 4; three ALS to unidentified, n.d., 1903 Feb 5, and 1911 May 24; visiting card with ANS to unidentified, n.d.; and fragments from the libretto for Panurge.
    - Unidentified, n.d.; 1 item (2 p.); 17 cm., bound in volume, 32 cm. (Box FOLDER 200)
      ALS to "Bien cher collaborateur & ami," about his absence from Paris.
      Bound with: two photographs of Massenet; ALS to George Durrieu, 1909 Jul 4; two ALS to unidentified, 1903 Feb 5, and 1911 May 24; two visiting cards with ANS to unidentified, n.d.; and fragments from the libretto for Panurge.
    - Unidentified, 1903 Feb 5; 1 item (3 p.); 18 cm., bound in volume, 32 cm. (Box FOLDER 200)
      ALS, "en voyage dans le Midi," to "Monsieur,"declining a collaboration.
      Bound with: two photographs of Massenet; ALS to George Durrieu, 1909 Jul 4; two ALS to unidentified, n.d. and 1911 May 24; two visiting cards with ANS to unidentified, n.d.; and fragments from the libretto for Panurge.
    - Unidentified, 1911 May 24; 1 item (1 p.); 17 cm., bound in volume, 32 cm. (Box FOLDER 200)
      Bound with: Two photographs of Massenet; ALS to George Durrieu, 1909 Jul 4; two ALS to unidentified, n.d. and 1903 Feb 5; two visiting cards with ANS to unidentified, n.d.; and fragments from the libretto for Panurge.
    - Unidentified, n.d.; 1 item (visiting card); 6 x 10 cm., bound in volume, 32 cm. (Box FOLDER 200)
      Printed visiting card with ANS about a missed meeting.
      Bound with: Two photographs of Massenet; visiting card with ANS to unidentified, n.d.; ALS to George Durrieu, 1909 Jul 4; three ALS to unidentified, n.d., 1903 Feb 5, and 1911 May 24; and fragments from the libretto for Panurge.
    - Unidentified, 1897-1905, n.d.; 8 items. (Box Folder 177)
      Five ALS to "Chère Mademoiselle," 1897 Dec 3, Paris, about a meeting, 1898 Mar 12, to a singer about her performance in England and referring to La Navarraise, 1905 Nov 9, about a meeting, undated, "de passage, Hôtel du Cap,"about his health and travels, and no place, about a meeting and referring to Cendrillon; two ALS to "Monsieur," 1901 May 19, Aix-les-Bains, and n.y. Dec 29, Paris, about his recipient's "Confessions" and poems; and ALS, "à la campagne," 1899 Jun 26, acknowledging a letter and referringt to his recipient's performance.
    - Unidentified, 1876-1912; 11 items. (Box Folder 178)
      Eleven ALS, most thanking his recipients, or about meetings or travel.
    - Unidentified, 1877-[1906?]; 5 items. (Box Folder 179)
      Three ALS to "Madame," Paris, 1877 May, about tickets for a performance, 1889 Jul 14, arranging a meeting at Harmann's about Esclarmonde, and [1906?], offering good wishes; and two ALS to "Monsieur," 1897 Nov 28, thanking his recipient, and Paris, 1901 Dec 23, declining an honor.
    - Unidentified, 1906-1911; 5 items. (Box Folder 180)
      ALS, 1906 Oct 30, referring to Thérèse; brief ALS to "Grand ami," 1907 Feb 24, referring to a premiere; ALS, 1907 May 9, about cancellation of a performance; ALS, 1909 May 6, about Bacchus; and ALS, 1911 Feb 4, arranging a meeting.
      Dates from annotations by recipients.
  - Music
    - Bacchus
      Opera, with libretto by Catulle Mendès.
      First performed 1909; published 1909 (vocal score).
      - Fragment from Bacchus, [ca. 1909?]; 1 ms. score fragment (1 leaf); 24 x 31 cm. (Box Oversize Folder 2)
        Addition for the funeral cortège in act four, with annotations indicating place of insertion. This passage appears on p. 263 of the vocal score published by Heugel (Paris, 1909).
    - Biblis
      Scène religieuse, for mezzo soprano, tenor, baritone, chorus (SATB) and orchestra, with text by Georges Boyer. First performed 1886?; published 1887 (vocal score).
      - "Biblis / poëme de Georges Boyer; musique de J. Massenet", 1887-1912; 1 ms. score (107 leaves); 37 cm. (Box Volume 1)
        Score, holograph, inscribed to Raoul Gunsbourg, Paris, 1912 Mar. Other holograph annotations, dated 1887-1891, include brief references to Sibyl Sanderson and Manon.
    - Cigale
      Ballet, with libretto by Henri Cain.
      First performed 1904; published 1903 (piano score), 1904 (full score).
      - "Cigale: passage à intercaler", n.d.; 1 ms. score fragment (9 p.); 36 cm. (Box Oversize Folder 3)
        Addition for insertion between pages 25 and 26 of the score published by Heugel (Paris, 1904). Accompanied by a fragment of the printed proof, p. 25-28, with annotations showing revisions preceding and following the insertion.
        Plate no.: H. et Cie 21,468. (printed fragment).
    - Ecoute-moi Madeleine!
      Song, with words by Victor Hugo.
      - "Ecoute-moi Madeleine!: ballade de Victor Hugo: pour contralto / par Jules Massenet", [186-?]; 1 ms. score ([4] p.) + 1 ms. part ([3] p.); 31 cm. (Box Oversize Folder 4)
        Score and part, holograph, with dedication to Adeline Palianti.
        Voice part includes text for all verses.
    - Elégie-mélodie
      Solo for violoncello with piano accompaniment, from incidental music for Les erinnyes, tragédie antique, by Leconte de Lisle, arranged from "Mélodie," in Dix pièces de genre, op. 10, for piano solo. Incidental music for Les erinnyes first performed 1873; published 1872 (vocal score). Elégie-mélodie for violoncello published 1885.
      - "Phrase pour le violoncelle: tirée de la musique pour une pièce antique", 1873 Mar 3; 1 ms. score ([2] p.); 35 cm. (Box Oversize Folder 6)
        Score, holograph, inscribed to "Monsieur de Bailly."
    - Enfants
      Song, with text by Georges Boyer.
      Published 1882.
      - "Les enfants / poésie de Georges Boyer; musique de J. Massenet", [1882]; 1 printed score (5 p.); 34 cm. (Box Oversize Folder 5)
        Printed score, published by Hartmann (Paris, [1882]). Inscribed by Massenet to Mathilde Claude, on cover, 1882 May 17, and on a preliminary page. Incribed by Georges Boyer to Claude on a preliminary page.
        Cover: "No. 2 Pour Soprano (Ton original)".
        Pl. no.: G. H. 1316.(2).
      - Quotation from Les enfants, 1896; 1 item (1 sheet); 10 x 19 cm. (Box Folder 182)
        Excerpt showing vocal line only, signed and dated at Paris.
        Purchased from Christie's (Int.) S. A. on the Library Associates Endowment Fund.
    - Espada
      Ballet, with libretto by Henri de Rothschild (attributed to René Maugars).
      First performed 1908; published 1908.
      - Fragment from Espada, n.d.; 1 ms. score fragment ([2] p.); 18 x 28 cm. (Box Folder 183)
        Fragment in short score.
        On verso: sketch fragment of an unidentified song.
    - Eve
      Oratorio, with libretto by Louis Gallet.
      First performed 1875.
      - "Eve / Massenet", [1875]; 1 ms. part (5, [17] p.); 36 cm. (Box Oversize Folder 7)
        Soprano part, holograph, with performance markings by an unidentified singer.
        Title from cover, written in an unidentified hand.
        Purchased from Moirandat Company AG on the Library Associates Endowment Fund.
    - Grillon du foyer
      Incidental music, for the play by Ludovic de Francmesnil, based on The Cricket on the Hearth by Charles Dickens. First performed 1904; published 1923 (vocal score).
      - "Le grillon du foyer de M. L. de Francmesnil / musique de scène par M. Massenet", [ca. 1904]; 1 ms. score ([15] leaves); 37 cm. (Box Volume 2)
        Score, holograph, with printer's markings, inscribed to Paul Ginisty, Théâtre de l'Odéon, 1904.
        T.p.: "moments musicaux par M. Massenet"; changed to "musique de scène par M. Massenet".
        T.p.: "Théâtre de l'Odeon, directeur: M. P. Ginisty".
        Leaves following title leaf are numbered 1-4, 1-2, and 5-12.
    - Grisélidis. Vocal score
      Opera, with libretto by Armade Silvestre and Eugène Morand.
      First performed 1901; published 1901.
      - "Grisélidis: prologue", 1894; 1 ms. vocal score (23 leaves); 36 cm. (Box Volume 3)
        Prologue, in vocal score, holograph, with revisions and printer's markings. Two annotations in margins are dated 1895 Jul 14 and 15.
    - Jongleur de Notre-Dame. Vocal score
      Opera, with libretto by Maurice Léna, based on Le jongleur de Notre-Dame, from L'étui de nacre, by Anatole France. First performed 1902; published 1901.
      - "Le jongleur de Notre-Dame: miracle en 3 actes / poème de M. Léna; musique de J. Massenet", [ca. 1901]; 1 ms. vocal score (131, [1] p.); 31 cm. (Box Folder 184)
        Vocal score, copyist's manuscript. A preliminary page is stamped "Pierre Broallier, docteur en droit". Accompanied by "Le Jongleur de Notre-Dame," by Pierre Soccanne, clipping from an unidentified newspaper.
        Caption: "Paris, Heugel, edit.".
    - Orphelines
      Song, with text by L. Landau.
      Composed 1906; also orchestrated.
      - "Orphelines / poésie de Ludana; musique de J. Massenet", [ca. 1906?]; 1 ms. score (4 p.); 35 cm. (Box Oversize Folder 9)
        Score for voice and string orchestra, holograph, with conductor's markings.
        Purchased from Erasmushaus on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund.
    - Panurge
      Opera, with libretto by Maurice Boukay and George Spitzmuller, after Rabelais.
      First performed, posthumously, 1913; published 1912 (vocal score).
      - Fragment from libretto for Panurge, [ca. 1912]; 1 item (1 p.); 20 cm. (Box Folder 185)
        Additional lines for the libretto, sent by Massenet to Georges Spitzmuller.
        Annotated by Massenet: "Panurge, 3e acte."
      - Fragments from libretto for Panurge, [ca. 1912]; 1 item ([4] p.); 32 cm., bound in volume, 32 cm. (Box FOLDER 200)
        Fragments from Acts 1 and 2, revised.
        Bound with: Two photographs of Massenet; ALS to George Durrieu, 1909 Jul 4; three ALS to unidentified, n.d., 1903 Feb 5, and 1911 May 24; and two visiting card with ANS to unidentified, n.d.
    - Plus vite
      Song, with text by Hélène Vacaresco. Published 1892.
      - "Plus vite / musique de J. Massenet; poésie de Hélène Vacaresco", 1892-94; 1 printed score (5 p.); 31 cm. (Box Oversize Folder 10)
        Printed score published by Heugel (Paris, c1892), inscribed to "Mademoiselle Van Hoot, Festival de Namur," 1894.
        Cover: "No. 2, en sol majeur (ton original)".
        Pages have been cropped.
        Plate no.: H. et Cie 7675.(2).
    - Poème d'un soir
      Song cycle, with text by Georges Vanor.
      Published 1895.
      - "Poëme d'un soir / George Vanor; J. Massenet", 1895 Mar; 1 ms. score (18 leaves); 36 cm. (Box Volume 5)
        Score, holograph, with printer's markings for publication by Heugel. Each song is dated at Paris, 1895 Mar 2-4.
        Pl. no.: H.8215, H.8216, and H.8217 (manuscript printer's markings).
        Contents: "Antienne"; "Fleuramye"; "Defuncta nascuntur".
        Ex libris: C. Bertram Stinson.
        Purchased from Colin Coleman on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund.
    - Poëme d'hiver
      Song cycle, with text by Armand Silvestre. Published 1882.
      - "Poëme d'hiver d' Armand Silvestre / musique de J. Massenet", 1881-85; 1 ms. score ([22] leaves); 35 cm. (Box Volume 4)
        Score, holograph, dated at Paris, 1881, with revisions and printer's markings for publication by Georges Hartmann. Includes annotations, 1881 Jul-Sep, and inscription to Madame Joseph Michel, 1885 Feb.
        T.p.: "Poëme d'hyver" changed to "Poëme d'hiver".
        Bound by a former owner, with some loss of annotations in margins.
        Pl. no.: G.H.1329 (manuscript printer's annotation).
        Contents: "C'est au temps de la chrysanthème"; "Mon coeur est plein de toi comme une coupe d'or"; "Noël! En voyant dans ses langes l'enfant radieux"; "Tu l'as bien dit: je ne sais pas t'aimer!"; "Ah! Du moins, pour toi je veux être l'ami que cherchera ta main."
    - Roi de Lahore
      Opera, with libretto by Louis Gallet.
      First performed 1877; published 1877 (vocal score).
      - Fragments from Le roi de Lahore, [ca. 1877?]; 3 ms. score fragments (3 leaves); 19 x 28 cm. and smaller. (Box Folder 186)
        Score fragments. Accompanied by an additional unidentified fragment.
        Purchased from Eurl Eve on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund.
    - Rêverie sentimentale
      Song, with text by Mathylde Peyre. Published 1910.
      - "Rêverie sentimentale / musique de J. Massenet; poésie de Mathylde Peyre", 1910 Mar 20; 1 ms. score (3 p.); 36 cm. (Box Volume 6)
        Score, holograph, with printer's markings, dated at Monte Carlo and inscribed to Marie Kohn. Bound with a copy of the printed score published by Huegel (Paris, 1910), signed.
        Plate no.: H. & Cie 24,934 (manuscript printer's annotation and on printed score).
    - Sapho
      Opera, with text by Henri Cain and Arthur Bernède, after Alphonse Daudet.
      First performed 1897 (first version), 1909 (revision); published 1898? (vocal score), 1909? (full score).
      - "Sapho: 2d tableau nouveau, 3me acte: [partition?] d'orchestre", [1909]; 1 ms. score (76 leaves); 40 cm. (Box Volume 7)
        Additional scene for act 3, composed for the 1909 revision, holograph, with printer's markings. Accompanied by a blank sheet of score paper with notes identifying the manuscript, numbered "308" on verso.
        Pl. no.: H. & Cie. 18.814 (manuscript printer's marking).
    - Scènes de féerie
      Orchestral suite no. 6.
      - Fragment from Scènes de féerie, [ca. 1880-1881]; 1 ms. score fragment (1 leaf); 18 x 28 cm. (Box Folder 187)
        Fragment from a draft in short score, with revisions.
        Annotated by Massenet: "Scènes de féerie" and signed.
        The leaf is numbered "32".
        Purchased from William Reese Co. on the Library Associates Fund.
    - Songs. Selections
      Fleur et le papillon: song, with text by Victor Hugo. Composed 1862. Crucifix: song, with text by Alphonse de Lamartine. Composed 1862.
      - "La fleur et le papillon: pour contralto / poésie de Victor Hugo; mise en musique par Jules Massenet"; "Le crucifix: pour basse / poésie de Lamartine", 1862 Aug 23-26; 1 ms. score ([6] p.); 35 cm. (Box Oversize Folder 8)
        Score, holograph, dated 1862 Aug 25 (Le fleur) and Aug 26 (Le crucifix). A fragment of an unidentified song, present on the recto of the first page, is dated [1862] Aug 23.
    - Souvenirs d'enfance
      Song, with text by Hégésippe Moreau. Composed 1863.
      - "Souvenirs d'enfance / poésie d'Hégésippe Moreau; mélodie pour ténor par Jules Massenet", 1863 Aug; 1 ms. score ([3] p.) + 1 ms. part ([1] p.); 36 cm. (Box Oversize Folder 11)